I would like to invite you
أود أن أصطحبكم
to come along on a visit
في زيارة
to a dark continent.
إلى قارة معتمة.
It is the continent hidden
إنها قارة مخفية
under the surface of the earth.
تحت سطح الأرض.
It is largely unexplored,
وهي غير مكتشفة تمامًا،
poorly understood, and the stuff of legends.
مبهمة وتحوم حولها الأساطير.
But it is made also of dramatic landscapes
وتحتوي على مناظر طبيعية خلابة
like this huge underground chamber,
مثل هذا التجويف الأرضي الضخم،
and it is rich with surprising biological and mineralogical worlds.
وهي غنية بعوالم بيولوجية ومعدنية مدهشة.
Thanks to the efforts of intrepid voyagers in the last three centuries --
بفضل جهود الرحالة الجريئين على مدى القرون الثلاثة الماضية.
actually, we know also thanks to satellite technology, of course --
في الواقع، كذلك بفضل تكنولوجيا الأقمار الإصطناعية، بالتأكيد
we know almost every single square meter of our planet's surface.
نحن ملمون تقريبًا بكل متر مربع على سطح كوكبنا.
However, we know still very little about what is hidden inside the earth.
ومع ذلك، لا تزال معرفتنا بما يحويه باطن الأرض متواضعة جدًا.
Because a cave landscape, like this deep shaft in Italy, is hidden,
لأن منظر كهف طبيعي مثل هذا النفق العميق في إيطاليا يكون مخفيًا،
the potential of cave exploration -- the geographical dimension --
إمكانية اكتشاف الكهوف، والبعد الجغرافي
is poorly understood and unappreciated.
تعتبر مبهمة وغير مقدرة.
Because we are creatures living on the surface,
لأننا مخلوقات تعيش على السطح،
our perception of the inner side of the planet
أما ادراكنا لباطن الكوكب
is in some ways skewed,
فهو مشوه نوعًا ما.
as is that of the depth of the oceans
كما هو الأمر مع أعماق المحيطات
or of the upper atmosphere.
أو الغلاف الجوي العلوي.
However, since systematic cave exploration started about one century ago,
ومع ذلك، منذ أن بدأ استكتشاف الكهوف الممنهج منذ مايقرب من قرن من الزمان،
we know actually that caves exist in every continent of the world.
نعلم أن الكهوف موجودة في كل قارة حول العالم.
A single cave system, like Mammoth Cave, which is in Kentucky,
نظام كهفي وحيد مثل كهف الماموث، الموجود في ولاية كنتاكي.
can be as long as more than 600 kilometers.
قد يصل عمقه حتى 600 كيلومتر.
And an abyss like Krubera Voronya, which is in the Caucasus region,
وكهاوية مثل كروبيرا فورونيا الموجودة في إقليم القوقاز،
actually the deepest cave explored in the world,
في الواقع أعمق كهف تم اكتشافه في العالم،
can go as far as more than 2,000 meters below the surface.
قد يصل عمقه حتى 2000 متر تحت سطح الأرض.
That means a journey of weeks for a cave explorer.
مما يعني رحلة تستغرق أسابيعًا بالنسبة لمستكشف كهوف.
Caves form in karstic regions.
تكوين من الكهوف في مناطق الكارستك.
So karstic regions are areas of the world
المناطق الكارستكية هي مناطق من العالم
where the infiltrating water along cracks, fractures,
حيث الماء المتسلل على طول الشقوق والكسور
can easily dissolve soluble lithologies,
يمكن أن يذوّب بسهولة الصخور القابلة للذوبان،
forming a drainage system of tunnels, conduits --
مشكلًا نظام صرف صحي من الأنفاق والقنوات -
a three-dimensional network, actually.
في الواقع، شبكة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
Karstic regions cover almost 20 percent of the continents' surface,
تغطي المناطق الكارستية تقريبًا 20 بالمئة من سطح القارات،
and we know actually that speleologists in the last 50 years
ونعلم أن مستكشفي الكهوف خلال الخمسين سنة الماضية
have explored roughly 30,000 kilometers of cave passages around the world,
اكتشفوا تقريبا 30000 كيلومتر من ممرات الكهوف حول العالم،
which is a big number.
وهو رقم كبير.
But geologists have estimated that what is still missing,
ولكن علماء طبقات الأرض قدروا أن المتبقي،
to be discovered and mapped,
حتى يتم اكتشافه ورسمه في شكل خرائط،
is something around 10 million kilometers.
يمثل حوالي 10 مليون من الكيلومترات.
That means that for each meter of a cave that we already know,
الشيء الذي يعني أنه مقابل كل متر في كهف نعلمه مسبقًا،
that we have explored,
تم اكتشافه،
there are still some tens of kilometers of undiscovered passages.
ما تزال هنالك حوالي عشرات الكيلومترات من الممرات الغير مكتشفة.
That means that this is really an endless continent,
مما يعني أنها قارة لا حدود لها بحق،
and we will never be able to explore it completely.
ولن يكون بمقدورنا اسكتشافها تمامًا.
And this estimation is made without considering other types of caves,
وهذه التقديرات تم وضعها دون النظر إلى بقية أنواع الكهوف،
like, for example, inside glaciers or even volcanic caves,
كمثال لذلك، الأنهار الجليدية في الداخل وحتى الكهوف البركانية،
which are not karstic, but are formed by lava flows.
والتي تعتبر غير كارستية، ولكنها تشكلت نتاج تدفقات الحمم البركانية.
And if we have a look at other planets like, for example, Mars,
وإذا ما ألقينا نظرة على الكواكب الأخرى كالمريخ،
you will see that this characteristic
ستجدون أن هذه الخاصية
is not so specific of our home planet.
ليست مقصورة فقط على كوكبنا.
However, I will show to you now that we do not need to go to Mars
ومع ذلك، سأريكم أننا لسنا بحاجة إلى الذهاب إلى المريخ
to explore alien worlds.
لاستكشاف العوالم الغريبة.
I'm a speleologist, that means a cave explorer.
أنا مستكشف كهوف.
And I started with this passion when I was really young
وقد بدأت أتبع هذا الشغف عندما كنت يافعا
in the mountains not far from my hometown in North Italy,
في جبال لا تبعد كثيرا عن مسقط رأسي في شمالي إيطاليا،
in the karstic regions of the Alps and the Dolomites.
في المناطق الكارستية لجبال الألب والدولوميتز.
But soon, the quest for exploration brought me to the farthest corner
ولكن السعي وراء الاستكشاف سرعان ما قادني إلى أبعد زاوية
of the planet, searching for new potential entrances
في الكوكب، باحثًا عن مداخل محتملة
of this undiscovered continent.
لهذه القارة الغير مكتشفة.
And in 2009, I had the opportunity to visit the tepui table mountains,
وفي عام 2009 أتيحت لي فرصة زيارة سلسلة جبال تيبوي،
which are in the Orinoco and Amazon basins.
الواقعة في أورينوكو وأحواض الأمازون.
These massifs enchanted me from the first time I saw them.
لقد سحرتني هذه الكتل من أول نظرة.
They are surrounded by vertical, vertiginous rock walls
فهي محاطة بجدران صخرية رأسية مذهلة
with silvery waterfalls that are lost in the forest.
مع شلالات فضية يتدفق ماؤها إلى الغابة.
They really inspired in me a sense of wilderness,
ولّدت في داخلي الإحساس بالبرية،
with a soul older than millions and millions of years.
مع روح تعود إلى ملايين وملايين السنين.
And this dramatic landscape inspired among other things
ألهمت هذه المناظر الطبيعية الفاتنة ضمن أسباب أخرى
also Conan Doyle's "The Lost World" novel in 1912.
الكاتب كونان دويلي صاحب رواية "العالم المفقود" والتي صدرت عام 1912.
And they are, really, a lost world.
وهي حقًا تعتبر عالمًا مفقودًا.
Scientists consider those mountains as islands in time,
خلص العلماء إلى أن هذه الجبال كانت جزرًا في وقت ما،
being separated from the surrounding lowlands
انفصلت من الأراضي المنخفضة المحيطة بها
since tens of millions of years ago.
منذ عشرات ملايين السنين.
They are surrounded by up to 1,000-meter-high walls,
هي محاطة بجدران يبلغ طولها حتى 1000 متر،
resembling a fortress, impregnable by humans.
تشبه قلعة منيعة من قبل البشر.
And, in fact, only a few of these mountains have been climbed
وفي الواقع، القليل فقط من هذه الجبال تم تسلقها
and explored on their top.
واكتشافها.
These mountains contain also a scientific paradox:
تحيط بهذه الجبال مفارقة علمية:
They are made by quartz,
فهي مصنوعة من الكوارتز،
which is a very common mineral on the earth's crust,
وهو معدن شائع جدًا على القشرة الأرضية،
and the rock made up by quartz is called quartzite,
وتسمى الصخور المتكونة من الكوارتز بالكوارتزيت،
and quartzite is one of the hardest and least soluble minerals on earth.
ويعتبر الكوارتزيت من أصعب وأقل المعادن ذوبانًا على وجه الأرض.
So we do not expect at all to find a cave there.
لذلك فنحن لا نتوقع أبدًا أن نجد كهفًا هناك.
Despite this, in the last 10 years, speleologists from Italy,
وعلى الرغم من ذلك، خلال السنين العشر الماضية قام مستكشفو كهوف من إيطاليا،
Slovakia, Czech Republic, and, of course, Venezuela and Brazil,
وسلوفاكيا، وجمهورية تشيك، وبطبيعة الحال من فنزويلا والبرازيل،
have explored several caves in this area.
قاموا باكتشاف العديد من الكهوف في هذه المنطقة.
So how can it be possible?
اذا، كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك ممكنًا؟
To understand this contradiction, we have to consider the time factor,
حتى نفهم هذا النتاقض، نحن بحاجة إلى إخذ عامل الزمن في الحسبان،
because the history of the tepuis is extremely long,
بسبب أن تاريخ تبوي ضارب في القدم،
starting about 1.6 billion years ago with the formation of the rock,
حيث بدأ تشكيل الصخور منذ 1.6 مليون سنة خلت،
and then evolving with the uplift of the region 150 million years ago,
ثم تطور الأمر مع نهوض الإقليم منذ 150 مليون سنة خلت،
after the disruption of the Pangaea supercontinent
بعد تصدع العملاقة بانجيا
and the opening of the Atlantic Ocean.
وانفتاح المحيط الأطلنطي.
So you can imagine that the water had tens or even hundreds of millions of years
لذا لكم أن تتخيلوا أن الأمر احتاج إلى عشرات بل حتى مئات الملايين من السنين
to sculpt the strangest forms on the tepuis' surfaces,
حتى ينحت الماء تلك الأشكال الغريبة على سطوح تبوي،
but also to open the fractures and form stone cities, rock cities,
وحتى يفتح الشقوق ويشكل المدن الحصوية، والمدن الصخرية،
fields of towers which are characterized in the famous landscape of the tepuis.
وحقول الأبراج التي تميز المشهد الشهير في تبويز.
But nobody could have imagined
ولكن لم يكن بمقدور شخص أن يتخيل
what was happening inside a mountain in so long a time frame.
ما كان يحدث داخل جبل خلال كل هذه المدة من الزمن.
And so I was focusing in 2010 on one of those massifs,
لذك في عام 2010 كنت مركزًا على واحدة من هذه السلاسل الجبلية،
the Auyán-tepui, which is very famous because it hosts Angel Falls,
وهي أيان-تبوي الشهيرة جدًا، بسبب أنها تحتضن شلالات الملاك،
which is the highest waterfall in the world --
والتي تعتبر أعلى شلال في العالم
about 979 meters of vertical drop.
وتبلغ حوالي 979 متر على الوضع الرأسي.
And I was searching for hints of the existence of cave systems
وقد كنت أبحث عن إشارات لوجود أنظمة كهوف
through satellite images,
عن طريق صور الأقمار الإصطناعية،
and finally we identified an area of collapses of the surface --
وأخيرًا تعرفنا على منطقة انهيارات سطحية
so, big boulders, rock piles --
صخور كبيرة وأكوام صخور
and that means that there was a void below.
وذلك يعني أنه كان هنالك فراغ في الأسفل.
It was a clear indication that there was something inside the mountain.
إنها دلالة واضحة على وجود شيء ما داخل الجبل.
So we did several attempts to reach this area,
لذلك قمنا بعدة محاولات للوصول إلى تلك المنطقة،
by land and with a helicopter,
عن طريق اليابسة وعن طريق المروحية،
but it was really difficult because -- you have to imagine
ولكن ذلك كان صعبًا للغاية، بسبب أن...عليكم أن تتخيلوا
that these mountains are covered by clouds most of the year, by fog.
أن هذه الجبال محاطة بالغيوم على طول السنة، وكذلك الضباب.
There are strong winds,
وتوجد رياح قوية،
and there are almost 4,000 millimeters of rainfall per year,
وتسقط أمطار بمعدل 4000 ميليمتر في السنة،
so it's really, really difficult to find good conditions.
لذلك فإنه من الصعب جدًا جدًا أن تجد ظروفًا ملائمة.
And only in 2013 we finally landed on the spot
في عام 2013 استطعنا أخيرًا الهبوط على تلك البقعة
and we started the exploration of the cave.
ثم بدأنا عملية استكشاف الكهف.
The cave is huge.
الكهف ضخم.
It's a huge network under the surface of the tepui plateau,
إنها شبكة ضخمة تحت سطح هضبة تيبوي،
and in only ten days of expedition,
وخلال عشرة أيام فقط من الحملة،
we explored more than 20 kilometers of cave passages.
اكتشفنا أكثر من 20 كيلومتر من الممرات الكهفية.
And it's a huge network of underground rivers,
وهي تمثل شبكة ضخمة من الأنهار الجوفية،
channels, big rooms, extremely deep shafts.
قنوات، وغرف ضخمة، وأنفاق عميقة للغاية.
So it's really an incredible place.
لذلك فهو مكان لايصدق بحق.
And we named it Imawarì Yeuta.
وأطلقنا عليه اسم ايماواري يويتا.
That means, in the Pemón indigenous language, "The House of the Gods."
ذلك يعني في لغة البميون المحلية، "بيت الآلهة"
You have to imagine that indigenous people have never been there.
لكم أن تتخيلوا أن السكان الأصليين لم يكونوا هناك مطلقًا.
It was impossible for them to reach this area.
كان من المستحيل بالنسبة لهم الوصول إلى هذه المنطقة.
However, there were legends about the existence
ومع ذلك، كانت تحوم بعض الأساطير عن وجود
of a cave in the mountain.
كهف على الجبل.
So when we started the exploration,
لذلك عندما بدأنا الاستكشاف،
we had to explore with a great respect,
توجب علينا البحث مع توخي الإحترام الشديد،
both because of the religious beliefs of the indigenous people,
بسبب المعتقدات الدينية للسكان الأصليين،
but also because it was really a sacred place,
وأيضا بسبب أن المكان كان مقدسًا بحق،
because no human had entered there before.
لأنه لم يدخل إلى ذلك المكان انسان من قبل.
So we had to use special protocols
لذلك توجب علينا اتباع بروتوكولات خاصة
to not contaminate the environment with our presence,
حتى لا نلوث البيئة بوجودنا،
and we tried also to share with the community,
وحاولنا أيضا أن نتشارك الأمر مع المجتمع المحلي،
with the indigenous community, our discoveries.
أن نتشارك اكتشافاتنا مع السكان المحليين.
And the caves represent, really, a snapshot of the past.
يمثل الكهف حقًا لقطة من الماضي.
The time needed for their formation
الوقت الذي نحتاج لجمع تلك المعلومات
could be as long as 50 or even 100 million years,
قد يصل إلى 50 أو حتى مئات ملايين السنين،
which makes them possibly the oldest caves that we can explore on earth.
الشيء الذي ربما يجعلها أقدم الكهوف التي بمقدورنا اكتشافها على وجه الأرض.
What you can find there is really evidence of a lost world.
ما تجده هناك هو فعلًا دليل على عالم مفقود.
When you enter a quartzite cave,
عندما تدخل كهف كوارتزيت،
you have to completely forget what you know about caves --
لابد أن تنسى تمامًا ما تعرفه عن الكهوف
classic limestone caves or the touristic caves
الكهوف الجيرية الكلاسيكية أو الكهوف السياحية
that you can visit in several places in the world.
التي يمكنك زيارتها في عدة أماكن حول العالم.
Because what seems a simple stalactite here
لأن ما يبدو أنه رواسب كلسية بسيطة هنا
is not made by calcium carbonate, but is made by opal,
ليس مصنوعا من كاربونات الكالسيوم، ولكنه مصنوع من الأوبال،
and one of those stalactites can require tens of millions of years to be formed.
والواحد من تلك الرواسب الكلسية يتطلب عشرات الملايين من السنين حتى يتشكل.
But you can find even stranger forms, like these mushrooms of silica
ولكن قد تجد أشكالًا أغرب، مثل هذا الفطر من السيليكا
growing on a boulder.
النامي على الصخر.
And you can imagine our talks when we were exploring the cave.
ولكم أن تتخيلوا ما كان يدور بيننا من حديث حينما كنا نستكشف الكهف.
We were the first entering and discovering those unknown things,
كنا أول من يدخل ويكتشف هذه الأشياء المجهولة،
things like those monster eggs.
أشياء مثل بيض الوحش هذه.
And we were a bit scared because it was all a discovery,
وقد كنا خائفين بعض الشيئ لأن الأمر برمته كان استكشافًا،
and we didn't want to find a dinosaur.
ولم نكن نريد أن نجد ديناصورًا.
We didn't find a dinosaur.
ولحسن الحظ، لم نجد ديناصورًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, actually, we know that this kind of formation,
على كل حال، في الواقع، نعلم أن هذا النوع من التكوين،
after several studies,
بعد دراسات مستفيضة،
we know that these kinds of formations are living organisms.
نعلم أن هذا النوع من التكوينات هو كائنات حية.
They are bacterial colonies using silica to build mineral structures
هي مستعمرات بكتيرية تستخدم السيليكا حتى تبني هياكل معدنية
resembling stromatolites.
شبيهة بالستروماتوليتيس.
Stromatolites are some of the oldest forms of life that we can find on earth.
يعتبر الستروماتوليتيس بعضًا من أقدم أشكال الحياة التي يمكن أن نجدها على وجه الأرض.
And here in the tepuis,
وهنا في تيبوس،
the interesting thing is that these bacteria colonies have evolved
الشيء المثير للإهتمام أن هذه المستعمرات البكتيرية قد تطورت
in complete isolation from the external surface,
في عزلة تامة عن السطح الخارجي،
and without being in contact with humans.
ومن دون وجود تواصل بينها والبشر.
They have never been in contact with humans.
لم تكن على اتصال أبدًا مع البشر.
So the implications for science are enormous,
لذلك فإن سبل اشراك العلم متعددة،
because here you could find, for example, microbes
هنا على سبيل المثال، يمكنك أن تجد الميكروبات
that could be useful to resolve diseases in medicine,
والتي يمكن أن تكون مفيدة لعلاج الأمراض في الطب،
or you could find even a new kind of material with unknown properties.
أو قد تجد نوعًا جديدًا من المواد يتمتع بخصائص غير معروفة.
And, in fact, we discovered in the cave a new mineral structure for science,
وفي الحقيقة، اكتشفنا في الكهف هيكلًا معدنيًا جديدًا للعلم،
which is rossiantonite, a phosphate-sulfate.
وهو روسيانتونيت، سلفات كبريتات.
So whatever you find in the cave, even a small cricket,
لذا أيا كان ما تجده في الكهف، حتى وإن كان صرصارا صغيرا،
has evolved in the dark in complete isolation.
فقد تطور في العتمة وفي عزلة تامة.
And, really, everything that you can feel in the cave are real connections
وفي الحقيقة، أي شيئ تشعر به في الكهف يعتبر روابط حقيقية
between the biological and the mineralogical world.
بين العالم البيولوجي والعالم المعدني.
So as we explore this dark continent
لذلك بينما نحن نستكشف هذه القارة المعتمة
and discover its mineralogical and biological diversity and uniqueness,
ونكتشف تنوعها وتفردها البيولوجي والمعدني،
we will find probably clues about the origin of life on our planet
فمن المحتمل أن نجد أدلة عن أصل الحياة على كوكبنا
and on the relationship and evolution of life
وعن علاقة وتطور الحياة
in relationship with the mineral world.
المتعلق بالعالم المعدني.
What seems only a dark, empty environment
ماقد يبدو بيئة معتمة وفارغة
could be in reality a chest of wonders
قد يكون في الواقع صندوقًا من العجائب
full of useful information.
مليئًا بالمعلومات المفيدة.
With a team of Italian, Venezuelan and Brazilian speleologists,
بصحبة فريق من مستكشفي الكهوف من إيطاليا، وفنزويلا، والبرازيل
which is called La Venta Teraphosa,
والذي يدعى لافيتا تيرافوسا،
we will be back soon to Latin America,
سنعود قريبا إلى أمريكا اللاتينية،
because we want to explore other tepuis in the farthest areas of the Amazon.
لأننا نريد أن نستكشف مناطق أخرى في أقاصي الأمازون.
There are still very unknown mountains,
لازال هناك الكثير من الجبال غير المعروفة،
like Marahuaca, which is almost 3,000 meters high above sea level,
مثل ماراهواسا، والذي يبلغ ارتفاعه تقريبا 3000 متر عن سطح البحر،
or Aracà, which is in the upper region of Rio Negro in Brazil.
أو أراكا، الذي يقع في المنطقة العليا لريو نيجرو في البرازيل.
And we suppose that we could find there even bigger cave systems,
ونفترض أننا سنجد هناك أنظمة كهوف أكبر،
and each one with its own undiscovered world.
كل واحد منها وعالمه الغير مكتشف.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Francesco. Give me that to start so we don't forget.
برونو غيوساني: شكرا لك فرانسسكو. بدايةً حتى لا ننسى.
Francesco, you said we don't need to go to Mars to find alien life,
فرانسسكو، لقد قلت أننا لسنا بحاجة إلى الذهاب إلى المريخ حتى نكتشف حياة جديدة
and indeed, last time we spoke, you were in Sardinia
وفي الواقع، آخر مرة تحدثنا فيها، كنت في ساردينيا
and you were training European astronauts.
تدرب رواد الفضاء الأوروبيين.
So what do you, a speleologist, tell and teach to the astronauts?
فما الذي تقوله وتعلمه أنت مستكشف الكهوف لرواد الفضاء؟
Francesco Sauro: Yeah, we are -- it's a program of training
فرانسسكو ساورو: نعم، نحن... إنه برنامج تدريب داخل الكهوف
for not only European, but also NASA, Roskosmos, JAXA astronauts, in a cave.
ليس للأوروبيين فقط، ولكن أيضا وكالة الفضاء الأمريكية، وروسكوسموس، ورواد فضاء جاكسا.
So they stay in a cave for about one week in isolation.
فيمكثون قرابة أسبوع واحد في كهف معزولين عن العالم.
They have to work together in a real, real dangerous environment,
ويتوجب عليهم العمل معا في بيئة خطرة جدًا جدًا،
and it's a real alien environment for them because it's unusual.
وهي فعلًا بيئة غريبة عليهم لأنها غير اعتيادية.
It's always dark. They have to do science. They have a lot of tasks.
فهي دائما معتمة. عليهم القيام بأعمال البحث وعليهم واجبات كثيرة.
And it's very similar to a journey to Mars
وهي شبيهة فعلًا برحلة إلى المريخ
or the International Space Station.
أو محطة الفضاء العالمية.
BG: In principle. FS: Yes.
برنو: من حيث المبدأ. فرانسسكو: نعم
BG: I want to go back to one of the pictures
برونو: أود أن أعود إلى إحدى الصور
that was in your slide show,
التي كانت ضمن عرض الصور،
and it's just representative of the other photos --
وهي فعلا تمثل باقي الصور...
Weren't those photos amazing? Yeah?
أليست هذه الصور مدهشة؟ نعم؟
Audience: Yeah!
الحضور: نعم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
FS: I have to thank the photographers from the team La Venta,
فرانسسكو: لابد أن أوجه صوت شكر إلى المصورين من فريق لافينتا،
because all of those photos are from the photographers.
لأن كل هذه الصور هي عمل المصورين.
BG: You bring, actually, photographers with you in the expedition.
برونو: إذا، كنت تأخذ مصورين معك ضمن البعثة.
They're professionals, they're speleologists and photographers.
إنهم محترفون، إنهم مكتشفو كهوف ومصورون.
But when I look at these pictures, I wonder: there is zero light down there,
ولكن حينما أنظر إلى هذه الصور، فأنا أتعجب بسبب أنه لايوجد أدنى ضوء هناك في الأسفل،
and yet they look incredibly well-exposed.
وعلى الرغم من ذلك يبدو المكان واضحًا جدًا.
How do you take these pictures?
كيف تلتقطون هذه الصور؟
How do your colleagues, the photographers, take these pictures?
كيف يلتقط زملاؤك المصورون هذه الصور؟
FS: Yeah. They are working in a darkroom, basically,
فرانسسكو: نعم، أساسا هم يعملون في غرفة مظلمة،
so you can open the shutter of the camera
لذا تقوم بفتح مصراع الكاميرا
and use the lights to paint the environment.
وتستخدم الأضواء لتطلي بألوانها البيئة.
BG: So you're basically --
برونو: إذا أنتم أساسا...
FS: Yes. You can even keep the shutter open for one minute
فرانسسكو: نعم، يمكنك أن تبقي المصراع مفتوحا لدقيقة كاملة
and then paint the environment.
ثم تطلي البيئة.
The final result is what you want to achieve.
النتيجة النهائية هي ما تود انجازه.
BG: You spray the environment with light and that's what you get.
برونو: أنت ترش البيئة بالضوء وذلك ما تحصل عليه.
Maybe we can try this at home someday, I don't know.
ربما نجرب هذا في المنزل يومًا ما، لا أدري.
(Laughter)
(تصفيق)
BG: Francesco, grazie. FS: Grazie.
برونو: فرانسسكو، شكرا. فرانسسكو: شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)